if I wanted to develop an exercise
program that was specifically targeted
with the primary objective of keeping my
brain as healthy as long as possible not
necessarily my body composition or
muscle or strength or anything like that
um I wanted to do an exercise program
for that one could theoretically say
Okay lift weights a couple of days a
week in exactly what you mentioned you
know five to eight exercises whole body
couple sets each yeah that'd be two days
a week one day a week do something that
is closer let's just even say the
Norwegian 4x4 that's a great option yeah
four minutes of the highest amount of
work people get mad when you describe
this as four minutes of Max effort are
all out you can't go all out for four
minutes but the highest amount of work
you can do for four minutes rest for
four minutes and do it again I don't
really think friends like I cannot
imagine a world in which that
specificity matters yeah you don't have
to do the for you could probably do just
about any type yeah of
high-intensity endurance
conditioning work and it would probably
be the same but let's just say for
Simplicity you did 4x4 once or twice a
week was that those interventions I
think they were doing it three times a
week okay but if you're doing other
aerobic exercise and and resistance
training I think you're gonna yeah you
probably not going to need to do like a
4x4 three times a week that's that's
pretty damn hard especially for six
months of time yeah I'm going to say
realistically as an exercise scientist
I'll give you permission to cut that to
two yeah per week yeah and then maybe
one to two or three sessions a week of
the more lower
intensity standard endurance exercise
cardio whether this is even physical
activity walking yeah uh or would they
actually need to do more like 50 60%
heart rate for that kind of
cardiovascular adaptation so you know
this is the this is the the age-old
question is like it like what's the
exact intensity required to see a
specific adaptation I think that and
it's the same uh we did a we did a
podcast talking about the
4x4 on my podcast and um then somebody
was like well what if I can't maintain
my heart rate in that zone for that long
like just do yeah right do whatever you
can for four minutes and you right
you'll get better over time and so I
think it's I think it's the same thing
yeah like if it's a if it's a casual
stroll you're probably not getting um an
adaptation but you know equally if if a
brisk walk is hard work for you right
then that's going to be that that that's
going to be a good good place to be yeah
this one RS me up so much because I I
get it people want like specifically
numbers but I'm
so resistant to do that because it
doesn't actually matter usually yeah
it's a it's a rough concept of where
you're at so if those numbers help you
great but something like that um here's
the reality don't think that your brain
all of a sudden won't adapt yeah if you
do half that yeah yeah if you did one
day of lifting one day of intervals and
a couple of days of walking it's better
than the zero yeah it's a lot better
right so you don't have to hit that
minimum number to get any effect
whatsoever right probably getting closer
to that Final Destination but if that
takes you 6 months or 6 years to get to
where you can handle that that being
that little three you know protocol we
talked about it's fine yeah like get
there eventually and and you'll probably
get um much to the benefit which which
is
great this actually answers a big
question that I have dealt with a lot uh
you and I actually have a a paper
together again that you led where we
found physical strength predict did I
think it was 5% yeah of cognitive
function right and I'll I'll say that
again like physical strength predicted
5% of cognitive
function I have talked about people have
talked about at length how leg
strength how grip strength grip strength
fires people up right and the common
claim here is like a grip strength is
just a proxy for overall health yeah and
certainly true mhm um if you look at
research on folks that have dementia you
will see I think actually one paper
found I can't even think it was UK
biobank paper about a half a million
people in it found that I think
30% of Alzheimer's death was explained
by low grips rate yeah right not a small
number and there's a recent study
showing that Frailty proed like precedes
like Alzheimer by by several years on
average multiple years I imagine right
and and right if you're frail you're not
doing all the things that we know
continue to stimulate or support brain
function right so what I want you to
kill and perhaps this is the fifth thing
that'll irritate the internet that we're
going to call is the idea that this
stuff the grip strength leg strength is
exclusively an indirect or a correlation
right of course there's some yeah folks
who are struggling with dementia are
probably also then going to struggle
with movement and there'll be a
backwards direction right there there
would be a causation but it would kind
of be backwards yeah causation right so
and this horrible idea that strength is
only a correlation to brain health and
you just actually kind of answered the
question before which is like how is it
actually causal but then spell this out
as directly as possible so I can cut
this clip and send it to people every
damn time I get told it's just a
correlation technically people are right
a lot of this comes from epidemiological
research correlation isn't causation um
however there are several studies we
just talked about some where you
randomize somebody to a resistance
training intervention there's strength
improves brain function improves right
brain structure improves and actually
related to the point that you making in
that in one of those studies yes you see
sustained improvements in white matter
structure with two sessions a week but
you got improvements in cognitive
function with just one session a week
right so you don't there these effects
particularly if people aren't doing much
exercise are essentially linear and like
so
I if you could ask for a more
causal function and structure benefit
and in a dose response yeah so what else
do we ESS says it's causal right yeah
and people are so depending on the type
of research of course people are right
you you can't tell you can't tell
causation
however what people also don't
necessarily understand is that in a
perfect epidemiological study if you
could account for every confounder and
you know mediating and moderating
relationships what you have left is
causation that is like by that is a
definition of causation so yes
epidemiological studies technically
don't show causation but if you could
it's difficult because you don't always
get the variables you want right you can
determine causation from an
epidemiological study that is possible
that's allowed in you know a frequentist
model of Statistics I'll count that as
like 4.5 thing that internet's going to
get mad at yeah you don't think people
understand basic statistics with that so
um right people have worse physical
health right we know so in the study
that we did if you had higher uh blood
blood sugar high hb1 C you had lower
strength but I think that's also B
directional right you know more insulin
resistance that's going to worsen um
muscular function but um if we think
about the potential mechanisms by which
this happens you have uh if you're doing
things that improve strength that's a
direct neuromuscular stimulus we've
already talked about the importance of
stimulus the next important thing is
that your skeletal muscle is your
biggest and most important GL glucose
sink so if we're thinking about the
importance of energy
regulation then your muscle like the
more muscle you have and the more you
move it the greater amount of glucose
you can move through that system and
this I mean this has been done for
decades and decades and decades so your
your skeletal muscle and your physical
activity are two of the best ways to
improve glucose handling and energetic
handling more broadly and then the final
piece is that when you contract your
muscles you release a whole bunch of
stuff right your muscles are organs so
lactate bdnf m c irin Lac Fe like pick
your metabolite cines
spectrin like whatever like whatever it
is like pick your favorite metaboli dour
right um we're still discovering like
torine we're still discovering on a like
on a weekly basis the things that are
released during exercise that have broad
broad benefits so like all of that comes
together to suggest that
um yes it's a bidirectional relationship
but by improving muscular size and
strength and function and those usually
go together but not always depending on
you know who you are um that's there was
four or five if not more different
mechanisms that would directly Rel
relate to improvements in cognitive
function and brain health if you enjoyed
this clip you can watch the full episode
by clicking here